

professional summary

Currently completing a PhD at the UNSW Water Research Laboratory investigating approaches to forecast innundation and erosion hazards for an Australian coastal hazards Early Warning System. Chartered Professional coastal and maritime engineer (CPEng & RPEQ) with a variety of extensive skills in structural engineering, coastal modelling, and hydraulic modelling. Seven years of diverse experience as an engineering consultant, demonstrating adaptability and flexibility to work effectively in autonomous and team environments.

contact

Chris Leaman 507/150 Pacific Highway North Sydney NSW 2060 Email: ckleaman@gmail.com Phone: 0488 404 949

education

2018–22 **Doctor of Philosophy** (ongoing)

Sydney, New South Wales

The University of New South Wales - Water Research Laboratory
Research topic: 'Regional-Scale Forecasting for Coastal Storm Impact Early Warning Systems'

Key skills:

- Coastal processes: Wave runup, shoreline and dune erosion, storm impacts
- Remote sensing and analysis: Satellite imagery, beach video monitoring, Python workflows
- Communication: Technical & academic writing, stakeholder presentations

2007–10 **Bachelor of Engineering** (Extended Major in Civil Engineering)

Brisbane, Queensland

The University of Queensland

positions held

2017–18 **Structural Engineer (Maritime & Coastal)**

2011–16 Graduate Structural Engineer (Maritime & Coastal)

Brisbane, Queensland

Kellogg, Brown & Root

Key skills and responsibilities:

Coastal, hydraulic and hydrologic modelling

- Modelling coastal processes including waves and sediment transport using DELFT3D
- Building and developing TUFLOW models to simulate flood events
- Developing flood studies and risk assessments for regional towns and rail tracks

Structural engineering of maritime structures

- · Completing structural design and detailing of wharves, dolphins, sea walls and ramps
- Performing complex finite element analysis using Strand7
- Inspecting site works for design verification and construction support purposes

Programming and documentation

- Developing Excel VBA and Python scripts to perform large scale, complex analysis
- Writing technical reports, specifications and proposal documents

professional memberships

since 2017 Chartered Professional Engineer (CPEng) (Structural)
National Engineering Register (NER) (Structural)
Engineers Australia

hydraulic/coastal modelling projects

2015–2016 Callide Dam Operation Study

Biloela, Queensland

Department of Energy and Water Supply (Queensland Government) and SunWater

Investigated the feasibility of operating Callide Dam as a flood mitigation dam after the Feb 2015 flood event.

2015–2016 Dawson River Flood Study

Banana, Queensland

Banana Shire Council

Developed TUFLOW models and simulated future flood scenarios to identify areas of risk.

2014–15 Patterson River and Queenscliff Dredging Review

Melbourne, Victoria

Parks Victoria

Completed modelling of Port Philip bay to optimize Parks Victoria's dredging program at river entrances.

2014–15 **Wave Buoy Data Recovery, Processing and Management**

Deagon, Queensland

Coastal Impacts Unit (Queensland Government)

Produced and documented MATLAB and Python scripts to consolidate historical wave buoy data.

2012–14 **Jazan Refinery Sea Water Cooling System**

Jazan Economic City, Saudi Arabia

Saudi Aramco

Evaluated hydraulic performance of cooling system under varying operational conditions.

2011–12 **Browse LNG Port Operability Study**

James Price Point, Western Australia

Woodside Energy

Identified critical sea states for using wave hindcast data for use in mooring analysis.

structural engineering projects

2016–2018 Kingsford Smith Drive Upgrade

Brisbane, Queensland

Lendlease and Brisbane City Council

Performed detailed design of cantilever retaining wall structure for road widening over the Brisbane River.

2015 **Osborne No. 1 Berth Upgrade**

Adelaide, Queensland

Flinders Port Holdings Pty Ltd

Developed wharf strengthening concept design to enable berth to accommodate larger vessels.

2014–2018 Port of Brisbane Operations & Maintenance Studies

Brisbane, Queensland

Port of Brisbane Pty Ltd

Conducted assessment of various existing wharf structural components at the Port of Brisbane.

2014–15 **Burrum Heads Boat Ramp and Car Trailer Park**

Burrum Heads, Queensland

Department of Transport and Main Roads (Queensland Government)

Completed detail design new boat ramp facilities, groyne, shore protection and drainage works.

2014 Legacy Way Residential Property Condition Surveys

Indooroopilly, Queensland

Transcity Joint Venture

Conducted condition surveys of nearby residential buildings to assess impacts of construction works.

2012–13 Townsville Port Inner Harbour Expansion (TPIX)

Townsville, Queensland

Port of Townsville

Completed detailed design and site supervision of berth upgrade and new cruise terminal building works.

2012 East Swanson Dock Crane Unloading Verification

Melbourne, Victoria

Patrick Terminals

Assessed capacity of wharf under temporary loads imposed by new quay container crane unloading.

2011–14 **Gorgon LNG Construction Support**

Barrow Island, Western Australia

Chevron Australia

Performed detailed design and provided site support for a large steel mechanical barge ramp.

volunteer

2019–20 UNSW WRL Research Management Group (RMG)

Sydney, New South Wales

PhD student representative

The RMG identifies opportunities and addresses issues regarding WRL's research output.

- Managing creation of WRL webpage to showcase current PhD students and provide information to prospective students.
- Organising social events between research and project staff to encourage collaboration.

2012–15 Young Engineers Australia Queensland

Brisbane, Queensland

Treasurer

YEAQ is a special interest group of Engineers Australia aimed at supporting young engineers.

- Budgeted, managed and monitored the group's finances
- Attracted over \$25,000 in industry sponsorship during the '13-'14 financial year.
- Advised the committee on strategy to ensure events and initiatives were financially feasible.
- Responsible for financial administration; keeping up-to-date records and ensuring the group complied with internal processes and procedures.

2012–15 **IMPACT (KBR Graduate Program)**

Brisbane, Australia

Graduate Program Coordinator

IMPACT is a network of developing professionals with 0-7 years of experience within KBR.

- Involved on a state and national level to deliver training and social activities to graduates.
- Proposed and monitored budget for social activities.
- Coordinated Australia's participation in company-wide events, such as Green Week and Global Week.

select publications

Leaman, C.K., Harley, M.D., Splinter, K.D., Thran, M.C., Kinsela, M.A., Turner, I.L., 2020. A Storm Hazard Matrix combining coastal flooding and beach erosion. EarthArXiv [PREPRINT]

Leaman, C.K., Splinter, K.D., Harley, M.D., Turner, I.L., Kinsela, M.A., 2019. Could an early warning system have forecast the impacts of a recent coastal erosion event along the SE Australian coast? Australasian Coasts and Ports 2019 Conference: Future directions from 40 [degrees] S and beyond, Hobart, 10-13 September 2019 755.

Stewart, J.P., **Leaman, C.K.**, 2013. Validation of dredge plume modelling inputs. Coasts and Ports 2013: 21st Australasian Coastal and Ocean Engineering Conference and the 14th Australasian Port and Harbour Conference 715.

A full list of publications can be found on Google Scholar.